Finding Aid for the George Peabody College Photograph Collection
Special Collections Manuscripts and Rare Books
George Peabody College Photograph Collection
1870s-1979
Special Collections Manuscripts and Rare Books
MSS.0000
.1 linear_feet
History
George Peabody College traces its history to 1785 and the founding of Davidson Academy, which was chartered by the state of North Carolina, as it was still part of the Southwest Territories. In 1806 Davidson Academy became Cumberland College and some twenty years later it was renamed the University of Nashville. In 1875 the State Normal School opened as part of the University of Nashville. By 1889 the school was renamed the Peabody Normal College. The name school continues today as Peabody College a part of Vanderbilt University.
Scope and Content
The George Peabody College Photographic Archives contains approximately 20,000 images that document the history of the college from its earliest times as a school of the University of Nashville in the 1870’s to its merger with Vanderbilt University in 1979. The bulk of this collection dates from 1920 to the 1970’s.
The collection is organized into nineteen series that represent the major aspects of the collection. It contains photographs, lithographs, and printed reproductions from publications, negatives, and slides. The 19th century processes found in the collection include albumen prints, lithographs, and salted paper prints. The 20th century photographs consist mainly of black and white prints, with color photographs appearing more frequently in the 1970’s.
The photographs are arranged chronologically within each topic, sleeved in Mylar with ten enclosures per folder. The ( ) behind a folder listing denotes the number of folders within that topic.
The George Peabody College Photographic Archives is comprised of photographic materials created by dozens of Peabody College staff over a number of years and only transferred to the Vanderbilt University Special Collections and Archives after the merger in 1979.
- Series List
  - Series I: Academic Departments and Programs
    This series documents the actual activity of educating students at Peabody College and is instrumental in identifying teaching techniques and classroom scenes through the years. Included in this series are images of the Blair School of Music, the Knapp School of Country Life, and the Library School. The largest subject in this series is comprised of approximately 340 images depicting the teaching of nineteen different sports to physical education students.
  - Series II: Academic Symbols and Awards
    Symbols of George Peabody dominate this series with five folders dedicated to the portrayal of the man whose money made the college possible. Beside black and white photos it includes lithographs, images of George Peabody from publications, and a few original albumen prints. Other images about pertain to his birthplace, bust, statues, and tombstone. The awards photographs are primarily of the recipients of fellowships and scholarships awarded by the college. Included in this series are numerous types of logos used by the college over time.
  - Series III: Alumni
    This series consists primarily of images of alumni at a variety of events both on and off the campus. The majority of these images are from undated and unlabeled events held at state meetings across the country. These images are in the form of black and white snapshots sent in by alumni to be used in the alumni magazine, The Reflector. Another interesting set of photographs is from national educators meetings which alumni attended and then submitted to the college.
  - Series IV: Athletics
    The photographs in this series consist of images pertaining to inter-collegiate sports played by students at the college. The largest group is of Peabody College students who played football for Vanderbilt University in the 1970’s. Photographs of Peabody College students engaged in intramurals or in physical education classes can be found in Series XIII and I, respectively.
  - Series V: Board of Trust
    Photographs in this series contain scenes of Board of Trust members at annual meetings, in formal group photos, and in various social settings. They are primarily black andwhite though there are a few color images from the 1970’s. Portraits of board members can be found in the Portraits Series under the member’s name.
  - Series VI: Buildings
    One of the larger and more comprehensive, series six documents the history of the buildings on campus. Every building located or once located on Peabody’s campus from 1914 to 1979 can be found in this series. The photographs contain images of the construction, exterior, and interior of the buildings often from a number of angles and seasons and through the years as additions and modifications were made.
  - Series VII: Campus Events
    This series covers events held on campus and under the auspices of the college. The largest theme in this section are the images of college graduations on campus, 1915-1979 with many photographs of unidentified graduates posing in groups and during the ceremonies. Another interesting topic covered in here are photographs of the “All-State Picnic and Stunt Night.” This event was held every summer along with reunions of alumni on campus and consisted of a picnic and skits performed by alumni who were grouped by their home state. Other events recorded here are conferences, concerts, art exhibits, and student orientations.
  - Series VIII: Campus Features
    Campus Features contains aerial photographs and images of numerous campus scenes. The images are often those that are very familiar to students and alumni of Peabody College. Included in this series are winter scenes of the campus covered in snow and spring scenes of the large iris beds across the campus.
  - Series IX: Demonstration School
    The Demonstration School was an actual school that Peabody College used as a laboratory for student teachers and professors to apply new and experimental teaching concepts in a traditional school environment. This series documents the student activities, projects, and staff of this kindergarten through twelve school from the 1920’s to the 1970’s.
  - Series X: Faculty, Administrators, and Staff
    This series covers the activities and group photographs of the presidents, administrators, and staff of Peabody College. Included in this group are Faculty Wives Clubs, Staff Clubs, the Peabody Dames, and the Women’s Club. For individual photographs of faculty, administrators, and staff look in the Portraits series.
  - Series XI: Fraternities
    This series documents sixteen social and honors fraternities at Peabody College. The images consist of group photographs, fraternity activities, and sweethearts or cheerleaders from the 1950’s through the 1960’s.
  - Series XII: Sororities
    This consists of images of six sororities on campus documenting the social life of women in these groups. They contain photographs of various sorority activities ranging from rushing to banquets and teas.
  - Series XIII: Student Activities
    This series contains images of the numerous student activities held on campus through the years. It is a vast record of the banquets, dances, intramurals, clubs, parties, and events students participated in from 1914 to 1979. From these images once can see what being a student at Peabody College was like and how it changed through the years.
  - Series XIV: World War Two
    The images in this series are primarily of Army Air Corps cadets who were living and going to school on campus during the war. It shows them in classrooms, marching, and in social scenes with Peabody College co-eds. One folder contains images of unidentified alumni who were stationed overseas during the war.
  - Series XV: Nashville/Tennessee Scenes
    The photographs found in this series consist of images of Nashville and Tennessee that were included in the George Peabody College Photographic Archives. They contain images of John F. Kennedy during a campaign stop in Nashville and scenes of the Nashville flood of 1926. Other images located in this series are of the Parthenon and capitol building in Nashville.
  - Series XVI: Portraits
    The portraits series is an alphabetical listing of photographs of Peabody College presidents, administrators, staff, students, alumni, and visiting officials and lecturers. Included in this series are approximately two hundred and fifty unidentified portraits of individuals and families.
  - Series XVII: University of Nashville
    The University of Nashville series contains images of the George Peabody College campus before it was located on 21st Avenue. When the college was part of the University of Nashville it was located in downtown Nashville nearer to the Cumberland River. These images while few in number they do document the buildings of the school and offer a glimpse of some student activities. These photographs are primarily from the 1880’s to the early 1900’s.
  - Series XVIII: Oversize Photographs
    This series consists of panoramic images and photographs pasted together to form collages. The most images date from the 1930’s to the 1950’s and are of graduation breakfasts, formal group photographs, and picnics.
  - Series XIX: Slides
    There are approximately six hundred slides of campus scenes, buildings, and student activities in this series. The majority are color images from the 1960’s and 1970’s.
  - Series XX: Negatives
    Original negatives from the collection are located in this series and though most are unidentified some have been traced to photographs held in the collection. There are approximately 4,500 to 5,000 negatives in the collection.
- Series I: Academic Departments and Programs
  - Art Education (11)
  - Audio-Visual Department (2)
  - Bill Wilkerson Speech and Hearing Center
  - Blair Academy of Music –Blair String Quartet
  - Blair Academy of Music –Suzuki Violin Class
  - Business Education (2)
  - Child Study Center (5)
  - Computer Center
  - Curriculum Testing Laboratory
  - Dance Class (2)
  - Division of Surveys and Field Services
  - Drivers Education
  - Education Department (2)
  - Ford Instructional Secretary Program (2)
  - Geography Department
  - Health Education
  - History Department
  - Home Economics Department (5)
  - Honors Program (2)
  - Industrial Arts Education (4)
  - Kennedy Center
  - Knapp School of Country Life (2)
  - Korean Library Project (4)
  - Language Laboratory
  - Learning Resource Center
  - Library School (7)
  - Mathematics Department
  - Mental Deficiency Program
  - Mental Retardation Laboratory/Child Study Center (3)
  - Mobile Testing Laboratory
  - Music Education (3)
  - Music Education –Conferences
  - Music Education –Summer Clinics
  - Nursing Department
  - Overseas Program (2)
  - Peabody In Denmark (4)
  - Peace Corps Training Program
  - Physical Education –Archery (2)
  - Physical Education –Badminton (2)
  - Physical Education –Basketball (2)
  - Physical Education –Boxing
  - Physical Education –Field Hockey (4)
  - Physical Education –Football
  - Physical Education –Golf
  - Physical Education –Gym Class (3)
  - Physical Education –Gymnastics (6)
  - Physical Education –Kickball
  - Physical Education –Ping Pong
  - Physical Education –Riding
  - Physical Education –Softball
  - Physical Education –Square Dancing
  - Physical Education –Swimming (3)
  - Physical Education –Tennis
  - Physical Education –Track and Field
  - Physical Education –Volleyball
  - Physical Education –Wiskit
  - Placement Service
  - Project Re-Ed (2)
  - Psychology Department (3)
  - Sciences (5)
  - Special Education Department (2)
  - Student Teaching (7)
  - Study-Teach Program
  - Summer in Mexico Program (2)
  - Summer School (3)
  - Teaching Center (4)
- Series II: Academic Symbols and Awards
  - Award Winners
  - Carnegie Fellows (2)
  - China
  - Cooper, Wade H. Scholarship Club
  - Ford Scholarship Recipients
  - Fulbright Scholars
  - George Peabody (5)
  - George Peabodiana (6)
  - George Peabody Birthplace
  - George Peabody Bust at Hall of Fame, 1926
  - George Peabody Statues (2)
  - George Peabody Tombstone (2)
  - Logos (2)
  - Mathematics Contest Winners
  - Medals
  - Scholarship Recipients
  - Signs (2)
  - Sullivan Award Recipients (2)
- Series III: Alumni
  - Activities (37)
  - Alumni Elections
  - Alumni Officers
  - American Association of School Administrators Meeting, 1953 (4)
  - American Association of School Administrators Meeting, 1960 (3)
  - American Association of School Administrators Meetings, Undated (7)
  - Association for Supervision and Curriculum Development Meetings, Undated
  - Campaigns (2)
  - Class of 1965
  - Conference –Washington D.C., 1959 (3)
  - Executive Committee Meetings
  - Group Photographs
  - International Alumni Groups (2)
  - National Education Association Meeting –Miami Beach, Florida, 1952
  - National Education Association Meeting, 1957 (4)
  - National Education Association Meeting, Undated (6)
  - Reunions (2)
  - State Meetings –Alabama (3)
  - State Meetings –Arkansas
  - State Meetings -California
  - State Meetings –Florida (3)
  - State Meetings –Georgia (2)
  - State Meetings -Kansas
  - State Meetings –Kentucky
  - State Meetings –Louisiana (2)
  - State Meetings –Missouri
  - State Meetings –New Jersey
  - State Meetings –New Mexico (3)
  - State Meetings –North Carolina
  - State Meetings -Oklahoma
  - State Meetings –South Carolina
  - State Meetings –Tennessee, East (2)
  - State Meetings –Tennessee, Middle
  - State Meetings –Tennessee, West
  - State Meetings –Texas (5)
  - State Meetings –Virginia (2)
  - State Meetings –Washington D.C.
  - State Meetings –West Virginia
  - State Meetings –Wisconsin
  - T. S. T. A. Meeting –Undated
- Series IV: Athletics
  - Baseball
  - Basketball (2)
  - Football (8)
  - Golf
  - Gymnastics
  - Soccer
  - Tennis
  - Volleyball
  - Vanderbilt Rivalry
- Series V: Board of Trust
  - Annual Meetings (9)
  - Group Photographs (11)
  - Social Scenes (8)
- Series VI: Buildings
  - Administration Building –Exterior (5)
  - Administration Building –Interior
  - Confederate Hall –Exterior (5)
  - Confederate Hall –Interior
  - Construction (2)
  - Demonstration School –Exterior (5)
  - Demonstration School –Interior (2)
  - Demonstration School –Fire
  - Development and Alumni Affairs Building (2)
  - East Hall –Exterior (5)
  - East Hall –Interior
  - Fine Arts Building (Cohen Memorial) –Construction (2)
  - Fine Arts Building (Cohen Memorial) –Exterior (4)
  - Fine Arts Building (Cohen Memorial) –Interior (3)
  - Fine Arts Building (Cohen Memorial) –Displays and Artwork (5)
  - Garrison Apartments –Construction
  - Garrison Apartments –Exterior
  - Garrison Apartments –Interior
  - Gillette Hall –Groundbreaking (2)
  - Gillette Hall –Construction
  - Gillette Hall –Exterior
  - Gillette Hall –Interior
  - Graduate Dormitory (North Hall) –Construction (2)
  - Graduate Dormitory (North Hall) –Exterior (8)
  - Graduate Dormitory (North Hall) –Interior
  - Greenhouse
  - Grey Building –Exterior
  - Home Economics Building (5)
  - Human Development Laboratory –Models
  - Human Development Laboratory –Construction and Groundbreaking
  - Human Development Laboratory -Exterior
  - Hume Chapel (3)
  - Industrial Arts Building –Exterior (6)
  - Industrial Arts Building –Interior (2)
  - Jessup Psychological Laboratory –Exterior (7)
  - Jessup Psychological Laboratory –Interior
  - Joint University Library –Construction (2)
  - Joint University Library –Exterior (3)
  - Joint University Library –Interior
  - Knapp Farm (4)
  - Knapp Farm –Animals (7)
  - Knapp Farm Club House –Exterior (3)
  - Knapp Farm Club House –Grounds (2)
  - Knapp Farm Club House –Interior (2)
  - Library –Exterior (10)
  - Library –Interior (4)
  - Maintenance Building –Exterior (2)
  - Mental Retardation Laboratory –Exterior
  - Mental Retardation Laboratory –Interior
  - Mental Retardation Laboratory –Ben Shahn Mosaic
  - Nursery School Building –Exterior (2)
  - Old Bookstore (Temporary Building) –Interior
  - Old Cafeteria (East Dormitory) –Interior
  - Old Student Center (Temporary Building) –Exterior
  - Old Student Center (Temporary Building) –Interior (2)
  - Payne Building –Dedication
  - Payne Building –Exterior (2)
  - Payne Building –Interior
  - President’s House
  - Smith Hall –Exterior (2)
  - Social-Religious Building –Construction
  - Social-Religious Building –Exterior (20)
  - Social Religious Building –Interior (3)
  - Student Center –Models and Construction
  - Student Center –Exterior
  - Student Center –Bookstore (3)
  - Student Center –Cafeteria (2)
  - Student Center –Cumberland Room (4)
  - Student Center –Lounges and Dining Rooms (3)
  - Student Center –Peabody Room (2)
  - Student Center –Post Office (2)
  - Student Christian Association House –Exterior
  - Student Religious Center –Exterior
  - Student Religious Center –Interior
  - Student Teachers Building –Exterior
  - Veterans Village –Construction
  - Veterans Village –Exterior (2)
  - Veterans Village –Interior
  - Ward Memorial Chapel
  - West Hall –Exterior (5)
  - West Hall –Interior
  - Bill Wilkerson Speech and Hearing Center –Exterior
  - Bill Wilkerson Speech and Hearing Center –Interior
  - Wrenne House –Exterior
  - Unidentified –Exterior (3)
  - Unidentified –Interior
  - University of Virginia Campus
- Series VII: Campus Events
  - All-State Picnic and Stunt Night, 1941
  - All-State Picnic and Stunt Night, 1947 (2)
  - All-State Picnic and Stunt Night, 1948 (2)
  - All-State Picnic and Stunt Night, 1949 (3)
  - All-State Picnic and Stunt Night, 1950 (6)
  - All-State Picnic and Stunt Night, 1951 (2)
  - All-State Picnic and Stunt Night, 1952
  - All-State Picnic and Stunt Night, 1953 (4)
  - All-State Picnic and Stunt Night, 1954 (2)
  - All-State Picnic and Stunt Night, 1956 (2)
  - All-State Picnic and Stunt Night, 1958 (3)
  - All-State Picnic and Stunt Night, 1959 (2)
  - All-State Picnic and Stunt Night, 1960 (2)
  - All-State Picnic and Stunt Night, 1961 (2)
  - All-State Picnic and Stunt Night, 1962 (2)
  - All-State Picnic and Stunt Night, 1963 (2)
  - All-State Picnic and Stunt Night, Undated (22)
  - Art Exhibits (2)
  - Art Exhibits Faculty
  - Art Exhibits Student (3)
  - Art Fairs (5)
  - Assemblies (5)
  - Banquets (2)
  - Blood Drives
  - Centennial Celebration 1975
  - Christmas Activities (7)
  - Christmas Dances
  - Christmas –Hanging of the Greens Ceremony (4)
  - Civics Institute
  - Concerts
  - Conferences and Workshops (23)
  - Conferences –Administrators
  - Conferences –Interstate School Building Service
  - Conferences –Reading Institutes/Clinics
  - Convocations (4)
  - Crabb, Alfred Leland –Historical Nashville Tours (7)
  - Cumberland Forest Music Festival (2)
  - Development Council (2)
  - Development Council –Activities (5)
  - Easter Sunrise Service, 1941
  - Elementary Circus (20)
  - Dance Festivals
  - Dance Performances (10)
  - Faculty Concerts
  - Faculty Minstrel Show
  - Faculty Receptions (7)
  - Faculty Skits
  - Foreign Visitors to Campus (4)
  - Founder’s Day
  - Gifts to the College (3)
  - Graduation, June 1915
  - Graduation, June 1917
  - Graduation, August 1918
  - Graduation, June 1919
  - Graduation, June 1920
  - Graduation, August 1920
  - Graduation, June 1922
  - Graduation, August 1922
  - Graduation, June 1923
  - Graduation, August 1923
  - Graduation, June 1924
  - Graduation, August 1924
  - Graduation, June 1925
  - Graduation, August 1925
  - Graduation, June 1926
  - Graduation, August 1926
  - Graduation, June 1927
  - Graduation, August 1927
  - Graduation, June 1928
  - Graduation, August 1928 (2)
  - Graduation, June 1929
  - Graduation, August 1929 (2)
  - Graduation, June 1930
  - Graduation, August 1930
  - Graduation, June 1931
  - Graduation, August 1931
  - Graduation, June 1932
  - Graduation, August 1932 (2)
  - Graduation, June 1933
  - Graduation, August 1933
  - Graduation, August 1934
  - Graduation, June 1934
  - Graduation, June 1935
  - Graduation, August 1935
  - Graduation, June 1936
  - Graduation, August 1936
  - Graduation, June 1937
  - Graduation, August 1937 (2)
  - Graduation, June 1938 (2)
  - Graduation, August 1938 (2)
  - Graduation, June 1939 (2)
  - Graduation, August 1939
  - Graduation, June 1940 (2)
  - Graduation, August 1940
  - Graduation, June 1941 (2)
  - Graduation, August 1941
  - Graduation, June 1942
  - Graduation, August 1942
  - Graduation, June 1943
  - Graduation, August 1943
  - Graduation, June 1944
  - Graduation, August 1944
  - Graduation, June 1945
  - Graduation, August 1945
  - Graduation, June 1946
  - Graduation, August 1946
  - Graduation, June 1947
  - Graduation, August 1947
  - Graduation, June 1948
  - Graduation, August 1948
  - Graduation, June 1949 (2)
  - Graduation, August 1949
  - Graduation, June 1950
  - Graduation, August 1950 (7)
  - Graduation, June 1951 (8)
  - Graduation, August 1951 (7)
  - Graduation, June 1952 (3)
  - Graduation, August 1952 (5)
  - Graduation, June 1953 (2)
  - Graduation, August 1953 (2)
  - Graduation, June 1954 (2)
  - Graduation, August 1954 (3)
  - Graduation, June 1955 (5)
  - Graduation, August 1955 (4)
  - Graduation, August 1956 (3)
  - Graduation, June 1957 (2)
  - Graduation, August 1957 (9)
  - Graduation, June 1958 (5)
  - Graduation, August 1958 (7)
  - Graduation, May 1959 (6)
  - Graduation, August 1959 (6)
  - Graduation, June 1960 (7)
  - Graduation, August 1960 (7)
  - Graduation, June 1961 (7)
  - Graduation, August 1961 (6)
  - Graduation, June 1962 (7)
  - Graduation, August 1962 (3)
  - Graduation, June 1963 (5)
  - Graduation, August 1963 (2)
  - Graduation, May 1964 (2)
  - Graduation, August 1964 (2)
  - Graduation, June 1965 (4)
  - Graduation, August 1965 (3)
  - Graduation, June 1966 (4)
  - Graduation, August 1966 (4)
  - Graduation, June 1967 (4)
  - Graduation, August 1967 (4)
  - Graduation, June 1968 (4)
  - Graduation, August 1968 (2)
  - Graduation, May 1969 (7)
  - Graduation, August 1969 (3)
  - Graduation, May 1970 (7)
  - Graduation, August 1970 (5)
  - Graduation, May 1971 (5)
  - Graduation, August 1971 (3)
  - Graduation, May 1972 (2)
  - Graduation, August 1972 (3)
  - Graduation, May 1973 (3)
  - Graduation, August 1973 (2)
  - Graduation, May 1974 (6)
  - Graduation, August 1974 (4)
  - Graduation, May 1975 (4)
  - Graduation, August 1975 (2)
  - Graduation, May 1976 (3)
  - Graduation, August 1977
  - Graduation, May 1979 (2)
  - Graduation –Undated (57)
  - Helicopter Visit –Summer, 1950
  - Humanities Festivals
  - Inauguration of President Sidney C. Garrison, 1937 (6)
  - Industrial Arts Exhibit (2)
  - Inter-American Night
  - International Center
  - International Fair (9)
  - Institute for Brazilian Studies/President Enrico Gaspar Dutra Visit (7)
  - Johnson, Lyndon Baines Visit, 1960 (2)
  - Jesse Jones Lectures
  - Kennedy Center Establishment
  - Korean Assembly
  - Library School Activities (8)
  - Library School Activities –Frances Neel Cheney Retirement, July 7, 1976 (3)
  - May Day 1929
  - McGovern, George Press Conference, 1968
  - Morning Coffees
  - Musical Performances (2)
  - Musical Performances –The Messiah (3)
  - National Science Foundation Institute
  - Open Houses (2)
  - Opera (8)
  - Opera –Devil and Daniel Webster, 1962
  - Opera –The King and I, 1962 (3)
  - Opera –The Maid as Mistress, 1962
  - Opera –The Medium, 1959
  - Opera –The Mikado, 1963
  - Opera –South Pacific, 1961 (2)
  - Opera –The Telephone, 1959
  - Orientations
  - Orientation, 1958 (3)
  - Orientation, 1959 (4)
  - Orientation, 1960 (2)
  - Orientation, 1961 (2)
  - Orientation, 1962 (3)
  - Orientation, 1963 (2)
  - Orientation, 1969
  - Peabody Aid Society (3)
  - Peabody Forums
  - Peabody College Radio Programs
  - Peabody Family Visit, May 1970
  - Peabody Women’s Club (2)